I'm in Singapore and I'm about to go on
stage in just a few minutes I have not
given a presentation for over a year now
I was in a little fender-bender a while
back and so I took a little bit of time
off there's this sense of urgency now
the global dollar standard was put in
place by a series of accidental events
that were very fortunate for the United
States because it gave us an advantage
over the rest of the world but our
politicians over the past decade or so
have abused this privilege as though it
was their birthright and now the rest of
the world are turning their backs on the
US dollar standard this is going to
cause a financial calamity the likes of
which we've never seen before and it's
going to be devastating for most people
I don't want this to happen but the
damage has already been done so I'm
going around trying to alert people and
show them how they can protect
themselves and turn this into a great
opportunity for themselves there's
always one result from what we are doing
right now expanding the currency
supplies all over this one result and it
is higher gold and silver prices I love
America at least the America that the
founding fathers created and I'm hoping
that people get interested in this so
that they'll see that what made America
great is the answer to our problems to
get back to free markets free people and
sound money our own history proves that
this is the road to maximum prosperity
we are entering a period of financial
crisis that is the greatest the world
has ever known the wealth transfer that
will take place during this decade is
the greatest wealth transfer in history
wealth is never destroyed it is merely
transferred and that means that on the
opposite side of every crisis there is
an opportunity the great news is that
all you have to do is to turn this
crisis into your great opportunity is to
educate yourself I believe that the best
investment that you can make in your
lifetime is your own education education
on the history of money education on
finance education on how the global
economy works education on how all of
these guys the central bankers with soft
market how they can cheat you how they
can scan you if you learn what is going
on and how the financial world works you
can put yourself on the correct side of
this wealth transfer Winston Churchill
once said that the further you look into
the past
the further that you can see into the
future this program is all about
creating your own crystal ball being
able to gaze into the future being able
to change this crisis the greatest
crisis in the history of mankind into
your great opportunity
[Music]
I was born in Salem Oregon in 1956 and
we moved to California when I was four
years old in 1960 but when I went to
school it was obvious after just the
fourth grade that there was something
different with me and by fifth grade I
was in remedial classes and it turned
out that I was dyslexic and teachers
were not taught to recognize that back
then I was always falling behind
everyone else when I would get a teacher
that would lecture instead of making us
read out of books I would just
absolutely Excel I suddenly become went
from the dumbest kid in class to the
smartest kid in all of the periods of
that class but the result was that you
know after a while I was in every single
remedial class and I just couldn't take
it and in tenth grade I dropped up
middle of 10th grade and I've never been
back to school I often say that in every
crisis there's an opportunity and in
this case the handicap of dyslexia has
also been a blessing because I couldn't
learn out of books and I couldn't take
notes I just had to remember everything
and I have the ability to my brains
wired a little bit differently I have
the ability to look at a chart today and
I know how it relates to a start that I
saw 10 years ago but it was back in
about the year 2000 when Steve Jobs of
Apple introduced OS 10 the world of
books opened up to me built right into
the operating system with a
text-to-speech program now I could just
have an assistant slice and scan my
books and turn them into text and email
me and then all I have to do is
highlight the text press a button and
the computer reads to me people are
turning to access that will keep their
value of it prices rise so much money
has been pumped into the system and
people are worried about inflation down
the road said to analysts right
professor of economics at the University
of Zurich the reflex is no longer
but what it's also done for me is I have
the ability to explain complex things to
people in a simple manner for some
reason and so I sort of made it my
mission to try and wake up the middle
class to let them know how the monetary
system works to let them know that there
is a major economic calamity coming
sometime down the road and it's most
likely within this decade that we're in
right now the US dollar is about 60
percent of the value of all the currency
on the planet and more than half of the
dollars reside outside the United States
the reason they every country has u.s.
dollars is first of all that's what
central banks uses the reserve currency
second of all oil is priced in dollars
so this is the world and what we what
you see here is that these are the
countries that are avoiding the US
dollar in trade they're doing bilateral
agreements where they'll either hold
each other's currency and settle that
way or they're establishing like right
now they're talking about a BRICS bag
Brazil Russia India China and South
Africa having a bank that will do
settlements between the countries
directly without using the US dollar
these countries they tried to avoid
using the US dollar like Iran tried and
we banned them from using Swift how many
of you here have made wire transfers
before so do you know what a swift
number is it's it's a code that you plug
in and this Swift system is what
transfers those dollars from one
person's account to another person's
account well
Iran decided that they were going to
sell oil only in Euros
they got banned from Swift but there's
countries right now coming up with a
replacement for swift and it doesn't use
the dollar it's the sucrose system and
Iraq started selling oil for euros in
Libya they were
talking about creating the gold dinar
and selling oil for gold so those are
the countries that are trying to use
something other than the dollar then
we've got gold competing with currency
and there's a lot of talk around here
about the gold dinar and there's people
that are actually using gold in some of
the countries over here and then in Utah
Utah has recognized gold and silver as
money again it's legal tender currency
in the state of Utah in the United
States and then you've got physical gold
accumulation I'll show you later that
China is accumulating an immense amount
of gold that all the countries with an
up arrow that's gold accumulation then
we have gold repatriation Germany has
been asking for their gold back and
they're getting it Venezuela has
repatriated their gold from the Bank of
England and then if we put this on a
time line here's the nails in the coffin
for the dollar standard and you will see
there's not a lot of time left this is
my evidence that I think is proof that
the death of the dollar is coming and
it's coming shortly Nixon ended Bretton
Woods and we went on the dollar standard
then the first nail in the coffin is
Iraq sells oil and euros the crisis of
2008 and we added 1.25 trillion to our
base money in the United States as we
add to the base currency people get
worried about inflation they start
rushing toward gold and silver Iran ends
oil fields in dollars and they're taking
commodities and trade for oil they're
taking in Turkey they take the local
currency and then buy gold in Turkey and
export the gold to Iran so they're
basically selling oil for gold they do
the same thing with India qe2
quantitative easing that's more currency
printing in the United States Libya
China and Russia bypassed the dollar
they did a bilateral trade agreement
where they hold each other's currency
and they do direct debt settlement
without
having the wire transfer u.s. dollars
Chinese president just recently said
that the dollar as the world's reserve
currency is a product of the past Utah
recognized silver and gold as money
China and Iran bypassed the US dollar
with a bilateral trade agreement then as
well at repatriates at school China and
Japan trade directly India and Japan
bypassing the US dollar Russia and Iran
trade directly Iran sells India oil for
rupees and commodities China and Brazil
trade directly Swiss citizens demand
gold repatriation African countries ban
the dollar in Zambia you can go to jail
if you use US dollars
quantitative easing number three they
have announced the Federal Reserve that
they're going to be there starting with
40 billion dollars of currencies that
are creating each month and now it jumps
to 85 billion dollars that's more than
one trillion a year and remember it took
200 years to go from no dollars to eight
hundred and twenty five billion and now
they're going to create a trillion every
year Iran trading energy for gold
Singapore removes tax on money
Germany repatriates one hundred and
fifty tons of gold from the New York
said the citizens of Netherland demand
gold repatriation Ecuador repatriates
part of its gold reserves Austrian
citizens demanding gold
repatriation China acknowledges
fundamental market shortage of gold and
now the Fed is increasing the rate of
printing when I said from 40 to 85
billion every month just over a trillion
per year so those are the nails in the
coffin for the dollar standard and if
you noticed they are all speeding up and
they're all happening right now you
don't have a whole lot of time and if
you wait too long then the opportunity
is gone it's going to fail why is the
dollar psychic
why is it not going to happen in stock
what will people think oh no looks high
technology we have computers now or the
internet and these are ridiculous
arguments
the truth is all fiat currencies have
failed and there's no reason why this
one worries me again so much is that
it's a global situation and so it's
going to cause problems on a global
basis and it's a trust breaking down and
you already seem to trust breaking down
the visit earlier because we're seeing
different countries exchange directly
with each other's currency sukima in a
dollar you've seen that in oil I'm going
to see it more and more and people are
just going to opt-out of the dollar and
you probably get to a point before the
whole thing collapses entirely where the
dollar is more or less used internal
United States and externally it's not
used as much because there'll be a lot
of Greenland made between nation states
outside the United States that we want
to use each other's currency and not at
all this isn't going to be pretty when
it happens I am NOT an end of world or a
doomsday guy all you can do is play the
hand that you are dealt if we go to a
new monetary system and I think it's
absolutely inevitable there's just too
much energy built up in in this one that
has to release it has to come crashing
down somehow when that happens there's
an enormous wealth transfer for people
that are on one side of the bed or
another and people don't realize that
whether they are they think they are
making a bet or not they are making the
bet they are involved this wealth
transfer affects everybody whether you
want to participate or not if you are
holding paper assets and paper
currencies you have bet one direction if
you're holding gold and and physical
assets you've bet the opposite direction
so these are changes in Chinese holdings
they are accumulating gold they are
getting rid of US Treasury bonds this is
gold held in China the green line is the
cumulative gold that's on this side this
scale so it's gone from about 700 tons
to almost 6,000 tons just since the year
2000 so this is their central bank
holdings this is their mine mine supply
but this is and my
researcher put all of this data together
you're the first people to see this this
is the amount of gold flowing through
the Hong Kong exchange that goes into
China and the past couple of years here
they have ramped up their buying they
know that the dollar standard is coming
to an end and they are protecting
themselves and you're probably going to
see gold back rememba someday the yuan
so this is an interesting chart changing
global influence so this is the
correlation to this basket of currencies
this basket of currencies if you add
them all up they're trading up or
they're trading down and this was pre
crisis so it's before 2008 so this is
from the International Monetary Fund
it's their data so from 2005 to 2008
this is the correlation of you know if
that basket of currencies was trading up
the dollar was probably doing about the
same thing as what it's saying that
Chinese renminbi a little less so and
then this is today the US dollar is done
for
I think is any question we're heading
for in the monetary system the question
is what will it consist of you know the
four choices are sort of a world of
multiple reserve currencies and Barry
Eichengreen Berkeley is the leading
proponent of this or leaving a scholar
on this topic the problem with that and
where I disagree with ICANN cleanness
there's no anchor in that system we did
have multiple reserve currencies before
in the 1920s he's right about that
and it was sterling in the dollar but
they were both anchored to gold and in
the post Bretton Woods world since 1944
it's been one reserve currency which is
the anchor and it was anchored to go
until 1971 since then the dollar has
been detached from gold but all the
other currencies are still linked to the
dollar so at the end of the day we've
had an anchor of some kind we've never
had a world of multiple reserve
currencies with no anchor I'm not sure
that's that stable the SDR is the second
choice the SDR is a basket currency
sponsored by the IMF at least for the
time being it's also printing money the
IMF literally prints the STRs and ships
them out to the members and their
reserves go up exactly the way the Fed
creates money and and bank reserves go
up but it's not backed by anything third
choice is gold some variation on the
gold standard and the fourth choice is
what I call chaos which is that nobody
does anything there's a lot of wishful
thinking there's a lot of denial there's
a lot of delay and we get to the point
where people just totally lose faith on
paper currencies go to hard assets and
we have a sequential collapse of paper
currencies around the world at which
point governments will have to react
with emergency measures that could
include coercion confiscation you know
various sorts of freezes on paper assets
could be a lot of things in that
scenario so to me it's multiple reserve
currencies SDR is gold or chaos I favor
gold but I fear that we may get chaos
I've talked about every 30 to 40 years
the world has a new monetary system and
the thing is that over the years
governments and the central and the
banks have basically screwed us more and
more and more and these new currency
systems are always created by the same
idiots that created the last one that
fell apart it's the big banks
the central banks and it's government's
that are creating these new systems each
time and each time the system they come
up with is a system that cheats the
population more and enriches the
government and the banks more it's a
system that transfers wealth at greater
and greater speeds you know this one is
going to fall apart just like all of the
others there's a difference this time
though there's the internet people are
connected all over the world information
is spreading and people are getting
educated so I'm hoping that we go back
to gold not a gold standard gold
standards suck I did a video on that
with a gold standard there's supposed to
be a certain amount of gold in the
vaults for each unit of currency in
other words the one to one ratio that is
the way it started and then they print
more receipts than gold that exists so
if we have gold standards we're going to
get scammed again if we used gold and
silver if the public gets educated
enough before all of this happens if we
went back to gold and silver then
governments can't scan us it limits
their ability to transfer wealth from
the population to the government and to
the banks a lot of people say that you
can't use gold and silver today because
they're too heavy and bulky and it's
completely wrong
you could put gold and silver in a vault
and you can make payments to somebody by
transferring ownership of nanograms
grams or ounces of gold and silver from
one person's account to another by means
of a check a credit card or even your
cell phone
if we go back to a gold-backed currency
hold back US dollars at that point I
think the minimum scam
that the US could get away with which
means the minimum number of dollars in
existence they could make convertible
into gold would be the dollars that are
held in foreign central banks that would
be similar to the Bretton Woods system
that we had from 1944 to 71 well I did
some analysis on this when I was writing
the book back in 2005 and back then it
required $20,000 an ounce gold for the
Treasury to have enough gold to cover
those dollars or the New York Fed
actually and if they were going to back
all of the dollars you're talking gold
measured in the hundreds of thousands of
dollars per ounce there just isn't that
much gold and there's a whole lot of
currency we keep on printing it every
minute of every day
[Music]
this is gold and how it accounts for
currency supply this is our base money
in the United States which was gold back
here from 1900 until the Federal Reserve
the amount of currency and circulation
and gold were the same then we
established the Federal Reserve and we
inflated for World War one and we had
more currency in circulation than we had
gold to Beckett there were some bank
runs in the 30s then Roosevelt unpaved
the dollar from gold and Gold's value
rose from $20 an ounce to $35 an ounce
and when it did the value of the gold
held at the US Treasury rose to meet the
value of all the currency that was
printed in the meantime here's the same
chart again but now I'm taking it out to
1971 and what you see is these gold
inflows during World War one during
World War two it's another 117 percent
gold increase this is what made the
United States a superpower it's all
financial it isn't our war machine
necessarily it's it's all the gold
inflows that we got because everybody
else was at war and we were isolated
from it and they had to pay us for all
their consumer goods and so on and then
we jumped into the war and we inflated
and then in about 1959 countries started
figuring out that we didn't have all the
gold you know we were printing more
dollars than gold that we had to back it
and under the Bretton Woods system they
could go to the New York Fed and turn in
their dollars for gold at $35 per ounce
only foreign central bank's individuals
could do that
so gold started flowing out in the u.s.
lost 50% of its gold from 59 to 71 and
in the meantime we kept on printing
currency if this had continued until it
got down to zero if there was one more
dollar out there that laid claim the
gold that came in and said we want our
gold for currency and there was no gold
to back it up
the entire world monetary system would
have come crashing down so Nixon had to
take us off of
the Bretton Woods system the last
vestiges of the gold standard in August
15th of 71 so here's the same chart
again there's the first chart and the
second chart 271 and now I'm taking it
out to 85 and I'm adding a second line
here
how many people would agree that credit
cards are replacing cash in circulation
yeah
credit cards you use your credit card
more and more every year right use cash
less and less well this is outstanding
credit card balances it's called
revolving credit outstanding is the name
of the chart that you get from the
Federal Reserve when you charge
something on a credit card you create
currency the bank didn't actually loan
you anything they invented numbers and
then they have the gall to charge you
interest if you don't pay those numbers
back on time but so the thing is that
the merchant that you're paying the
restaurant or the grocery store that
merchants checking account can't tell
the difference between the credit
dollars that you created or the cash
dollars that you Pam
so to that merchants checking account it
all looks the same and those dollars
that you created stay in circulation
until somebody saves them up and pays
down credit card debt so unpaid credit
card balances I include as part of the
cash in circulation and in 1971 Nixon
took us off the gold standard and gold
became a freely traded separate
commodity slash money and it did an
accounting of the currency supply there
was quite a while here where we could
have gone back on the gold standard the
value of the gold of the Treasury
exceeded all the dollars printed from
George Washington to Jimmy Carter and
for a week or so a couple of weeks it
exceeded out base money plus outstanding
revolving credit so here's the same
chart again that was to 1985 and now I'm
going to take it out to today and so
there's that 1980 peak where it's shot
past base money and base money plus
outstanding revolving credit and then we
get to the crisis of o8
and ben bernanke oh by the way instead
of billions we're now measuring in
trillions so we started in millions and
then it went to billions and now it's
trillions so we did the bailouts and all
the quantitative easing and that's what
the currency supply looks like today and
then they announced quantitative easing
3 which is that 85 billion a month that
they're creating and they think they're
going to have to do it until about 2015
so here's the projection for gold
covering the currency supply today would
be thirteen thousand four hundred
dollars per ounce gold for history
repeat for gold to do the same thing
that it did in 1934 and in nineteen
eighty and believe me
it shocked people in nineteen in the
1970s when gold was $35 an ounce and
Nixon took us off the Bretton Woods
system all the economists were
predicting that gold was going to go
down because now there was going to be
no more monetary demand for it
anybody that said gold was going to go
to a hundred bucks was considered an
absolute lunatic and it went to eight
hundred and fifty rose twenty-four times
its price well when I wrote my book we
were right here with base money so base
money plus outstanding low and credit it
took about six thousand dollars an ounce
for history rupee
today it takes for thirteen thousand
four hundred and if you include the same
overshoot remember in nineteen eighty it
didn't just cover base money but it shot
past it
twenty four thousand dollar an ounce
gold is what it would require to meet
that except we the Fed has announced
that they're going to keep on printing
currency until there's lower
unemployment and the economy gets back
on track and they think till 2015 so the
projected price according to the Fed and
history repeating if that was to if if
the Fed does this and then history
repeats and gold the the public gets
afraid of what the Federal Reserve is
doing and they rush toward gold and
silver to protect their purchasing power
gold would have to rise from there to
way up here and that
is $26,000 per ounce gold to cover if it
does the same overshoot we're talking
about $47,000 an ounce gold now I don't
even like to measure gold in dollars if
you measure it in a price price doesn't
mean anything it's the value how much
can you buy with the proceeds if we have
deflation and some of this currency
evaporates because it's all just numbers
that they type into a computer these
days if we have deflation maybe gold
peaks at $3,000 an ounce and the
currency supply collapses to way down
here somewhere and the Dow is at 1500
that means gold will still be double the
Dow you're still going to get 14 times
more paper assets one day than you can
buy today with them and it's probably
only a couple of years left that this is
going to take as you saw about how the
nails in the coffin of the dollar
standard how they're speeding up if we
have big inflation and the Dow goes to
30,000 maybe gold will be 60 thousand an
ounce and if we have hyperinflation the
Dow would be 30 trillion and gold would
be 60 trillion it doesn't matter in any
case gold would buy you 14 times more
paper assets than it does today so these
are the global assets here's the start
of the bond market here's the stock
market this is the value of real estate
on the planet and these are bank
deposits and there's gold now that
little slice of the pie is going to get
a lot bigger in just the next few years
and it's not going to do it by a whole
bunch more gold just appearing it's
going to do it by the price of other
assets going down or at least their
value going down and the value of gold
going up so the price of gold will
change that piece of the pie is going to
grow it was a lot bigger back in 1980
when gold was at 850 dollars it's going
to get a lot bigger today again but
today as you've seen it requires far far
higher prices so the death of the dollar
standard does how many people here
believe that I'm sort of predicting
what's going on in the future here
you can see that there's a new world
monetary system coming it happens every
30 to 40 years except this time instead
of a baby step off of gold we've got to
go from nothing back to something it's
going to be a worldwide convulsion the
scale of which has never been seen
before at the end of the day the
fundamental fundamental driver of gold
it's not so much the Gold's in the bull
markets where the dollars in a bear
market and people say well how high can
gold go and my answer is well how low
can the dollar go the answer is the
dollar can go to zero if you divide any
number by 0 the answer is infinity so
gold can go to infinity if a dollar goes
to zero now in the real world something
else will happen it's not the gold
becomes worth infinite number of dollars
it's more the case that the dollar just
falls off the stage the dollar hits the
hook so to speak and you'll count gold
in dollars to five thousand to ten
thousand at some point it will come a
time when you won't count golden dollars
and in one of those dollars won't count
people won't want dollars there is so
much opportunity in crisis it is
absolutely extraordinary that's just
what we're saying that that's history
you read any amount of history and I
don't mean last week I mean real history
you know returns a crisis it's when huge
fortunes will make terms of crisis it's
when human beings create and develop
newest technologies and new science and
new medicines in times of crisis there's
so much opportunity as long as you can
remain calm get educated be resourceful
it's challenge for most people is that
in crisis they don't a crisis market
which means they go into scarcity
they're going to lack they're going to
blame and none of those emotions are
resourceful for helping you solve
whatever challenge isn't funny
I believe that this is probably the
greatest opportunity of anyone's
lifetime there has never been a
situation where all of everything came
together just like this this is the
first time in history where all the
world's currencies are just fiat
currencies backed by nothing and if what
happened what I think is going to happen
happened this is the greatest wealth
transfer in history it's the greatest
opportunity and it'll never happen in
our lifetimes again so now we've learned
the following hidden secrets of money
there is a global loss of confidence in
the u.s. dollar that is accelerating
rapidly the change to a new monetary
system is inevitable and will most
likely be chaotic gold standards do not
work over long periods of time but gold
itself does the public contributes to
the massive amounts of currency creation
by using credit cards and signing loans
gold is already accounted for the
expansion of US dollars twice in the
last century and may likely do so again
so that's it for this episode I thank
you for watching and I hope you enjoyed
it I know I threw around a bunch of
astronomical prices for gold someday in
the future but it isn't the price
measured in dollars it's how much is its
value what is it worth how much stuff
can it purchase the price measured in
dollars or any currency for that matter
is just a bunch of numbers and it really
doesn't mean anything there are numbers
that are created by the world's central
banks by the commercial bank system and
we're forced to transact in these
currencies but in our next episode we're
going to clear away the smokescreen of
national currencies and show you how the
world monetary system really works and
how all national currencies have to
continue losing value it is not possible
for them to maintain purchasing power
over any reasonable period of time as
for the golden nails in the dollars
coffin it's only been a short while
since we filmed the presentation in
Singapore and already there are more of
the
so for an update visit hidden secrets of
money calm and in your free information
toolkit there's an exclusive
presentation on the latest developments
of the golden males in the dollars
coffin now I know this episode was kind
of serious and it might have you upset
right now but believe me it's not all
doom and gloom as I've said many many
times before there are these brief
moments in history where the safest
asset class the safe haven investment
for the last five thousand years also
becomes the asset class that has the
greatest potential gains in purchasing
power and I have bet my life on it
first I would became an investor back in
2002 and then I started telling
everybody about it I started warning
them what was going to happen with the
world economy and how to protect
themselves and I made it my mission to
educate as many as I could so in 2005 I
wrote my book and then I gave people a
means to protect themselves and opened
up goldsilver.com I believe that my team
and I have created the world's best
precious metals dealership because we
don't just sell gold and silver we are
gold and silver investors and what we
want to do is help you understand how to
get through what is coming to protect
yourself and to turn all of these bad
things around to your benefit so if you
decide that precious metals are for you
please visit gold silver calm we'd love
the opportunity to become your dealer
because we feel that we are more than a
dealer we are a partner with you and
we're on the same side of the fence as
you so thank you very much good luck
we'll see you at the exclusive
presentation at hidden secrets of money
Thanks and you think this is a man the
last boat situation let me ask you this
if you knew the site anak was going to
thinking you were on the Titanic you
know that it's going to be a lifeboat
situation coming up
would you like Windows available that's
what would you like to get in the life
of early get a nice seat maybe close to
the water very close a little to the
view supply right there in the middle
nice and comfy or you want to be one of
the last ones on the boat you're
jockeying for position to throw a kid
out to make room for you yeah so we I
feel life is situated depends how what
how you like your accommodations on the
lifeboat is whether you should be waking
your way towards the right now and I
will be edging by way towards us right
now Mike Melones hidden secrets of money
is made possible by the clients of gold
silver calm your continued loyalty and
support allows us to educate the public
on how to both protect themselves and
benefit in the turbulent times ahead to
all gold silver calm customers thank you
hidden secrets of money would not be
possible without you